Prerna Chikersal

APPLIED MACHINE LEARNING · HUMAN-COMPUTER INTERACTION · UBIQUITOUS COMPUTING · DATA SCIENCE · COMPUTER-MEDIATED COMMUNICATION

Professional Interests

I develop machine learning methods and systems to understand and augment human behavior, with the goal of improving health, wellbeing, and performance. For this purpose, I analyze multimodal data such as smartphone and wearable data, web interaction logs, text and speech data, and facial images by combining methods from statistics, speech processing, natural language processing, and computer vision. I also have experience developing mobile apps for human subject research, and qualitative method such as user interviews and thematic analysis.

Education

Carnegie Mellon University

Pittsburgh, PA, USA

Aug 2017 - Present

Ph.D. IN HUMAN-COMPUTER INTERACTION

- ADVISORS: Anind Dey and Mayank Goel
- RESEARCH FOCUS: Applied Machine Learning, Human-Computer Interaction, Ubiquitous Computing, Health Data Science
- THESIS: "Multimodal Behavioral Sensing for Precision Mental Health Care"

Carnegie Mellon University

Pittsburgh, PA, USA

M.S. IN HUMAN-COMPUTER INTERACTION

Aug 2017 - May 2022

- Completed during the Ph.D. in Human-Computer Interaction degree.
 RELEVANT COURSES: HCI Process and Theory, Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing, Cognitive Science Perspectives in HCI, Human-Al Interaction, and Computational Medicine.
- Carnegie Mellon University

Pittsburgh, PA, USA

M.S. IN ROBOTICS

Aug 2015 - Aug 2017

- COMMITTEE: Laura Dabbish (advisor), Louis-Philippe Morency, Marynel Vázquez
- COLLABORATORS: Anita Woolley, Maria Tomprou, Young Ji Kim
- THESIS: "Deep Structures of Collaboration"
- RELEVANT COURSES: Introduction to Machine Learning (PhD-level), Computer Vision, Human-Robot Interaction, Human Communication and Multimodal Computation, and Experimental Design for Social and Behavioral Sciences.

Nanyang Technological University

Singapore

B.Eng. IN Computer Science

Aug 2011 - May 2015

- First Class Honors and Specialization in Intelligent Systems
- THESIS ADVISOR: Erik Cambria
- Final Year Thesis: "Modeling Public Sentiment in Twitter" (A+ Grade)
- RELEVANT COURSES: Natural Language Processing, Neural Networks, Intelligent Agents, Artificial Intelligence, and Intro to Psychology.

Columbia University

New York, NY, USA

Jul 2014 - Aug 2014

Publications

SUMMER SCHOOL

PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE AND JOURNAL PAPERS

- Chikersal, P., Venkatesh, S., Masown, K., Walker, E., Quraishi, D., Dey, A., Goel, M., & Xia, Z. Predicting Multiple Sclerosis Outcomes during the COVID-19 Stay-at-Home Period: Observational Study Using Passively Sensed Behaviors and Digital Phenotyping. In *JMIR mental health (2022)*.
- Xu, X., **Chikersal, P.**, Dutcher, J. M., Sefidgar, Y. S., Seo, W., Tumminia, M. J., Villalba, D. K., Cohen, S., Creswell, K. G., Creswell, J. D., Doryab, A., Nurius, P. S., Riskin, E., Dey, A. K., & Mankoff, J. Leveraging Collaborative-Filtering for Personalized Behavior Modeling: A Case Study of Depression Detection among College Students. In *Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (Ubicomp 2021)*.
- Tomprou, M., Kim, Y. J., **Chikersal, P.**, Woolley, A. W., & Dabbish, L. (2021). Speaking out of turn: How video conferencing reduces vocal synchrony and collective intelligence. *PLOS ONE*.
- Chikersal, P., Doryab, A., Tumminia, M., Villalba, D., Dutcher, J., Liu, X., Cohen, S., Creswell, K., Mankoff, J., Creswell, D., Goel, M., & Dey, A. (2020). Detecting Depression and Predicting its Onset Using Longitudinal Symptoms Captured by Passive Sensing: A Machine Learning Approach With Robust Feature Selection. ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction (TOCHI 2020). (Presented at CHI 2021).
- Chikersal, P., Belgrave, D., Doherty, G, Enrique, A., Palacios, J., Richards, D., & Thieme, A. (2020). Understanding Client Support Strategies to Improve Clinical Outcomes in an Online Mental Health Intervention. In *Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI 2020)*. (Talk, Microsoft's Blog Post)

- Xu, X., **Chikersal, P.**, Doryab, A., Villalba, D., Dutcher, J. M., Tumminia, M. J., Althoff, T., Cohen, S., Creswell, K., Creswell, D., Mankoff, J., & Dey, A. K. (2019). Leveraging Routine Behavior and Contextually-Filtered Features for Depression Detection among College Students. In *Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (Ubicomp 2019)*.
- Doryab, A., Villalba, D. K., **Chikersal, P.**, Dutcher, J. M., Tumminia, M., Liu, X., Cohen, S., Creswell, K., Mankoff, J., Creswell, D., & Dey, A. K. (2019). Identifying Behavioral Phenotypes of Loneliness and Social Isolation with Passive Sensing: A Three-fold Analysis. In *Journal of medical Internet research (JMIR 2019)*.
- Chikersal, P., Tomprou, M., Kim, Y. J., Woolley, A. W., & Dabbish, L. (2017). Deep Structures of Collaboration: Physiological Correlates of Collective Intelligence and Group Satisfaction. In *Proceedings of the 20th ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW 2017)*.
- Chikersal, P., Poria, S., Cambria, E., Gelbukh, A., & Siong, C. E. (2015). Modelling Public Sentiment in Twitter: Using Linguistic Patterns to Enhance Supervised Learning. In *International Conference on Intelligent Text Processing and Computational Linguistics* (CICLing 2015) (pp. 49-65).

PEER-REVIEWED WORKSHOP PAPERS

- **Chikersal, P.**, Doherty, G, & Thieme, A. (2020). Towards Using AI to Augment Human Support in Digital Mental Healthcare. In *Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Workshop on Technology Ecosystems: Rethinking Resources for Mental Health*.
- Chikersal, P., Poria, S., & Cambria, E. (2015). SeNTU: Sentiment Analysis of Tweets by Combining a Rule-based Classifier with Supervised Learning. In *Proceedings of the 4th International Workshop on Semantic Evaluations* (pp. 647-651). Association for Computational Linguistics.

THESIS

- Chikersal, P. (2017, May). Deep Structures of Collaboration. Masters Thesis, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA, USA.
- Chikersal, P. (2015, May). Modelling Public Sentiment in Twitter. Bachelor Thesis, Nanyang Technological University, Singapore.

Awards & Fellowships.

1.	Awarded the Snap Research Fellowship (from Snapchat) – which "honors the brightest, most driven students who positively impacted research and product development during their internships at Snap".	Dec 2020
2.	Awarded the Grace Hopper Celebration (GHC) Scholarship – sponsors women who actively contribute to their community, to attend the Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing.	Jun 2020
3.	Awarded a Fellowship in Digital Health by the Center for Machine Learning and Health (CMLH) at CMU. Covers tuition, stipend, and \$3000 research expenses for 1 year.	Aug 2017 – Aug 2018
4.	Awarded a Research Scholarship by EPFL for NTU-EPFL's research exchange program.	Aug 2013
5.	Accepted into the Summer@EPFL Research Internship Program (0.03% acceptance rate; 1500 applications; fully funded).	Apr 2013
6.	2nd Prize in URECA@NTU Poster Competition – a research competition held for students participating in NTU's prestigious Undergraduate Research Experience on CAmpus program.	Mar 2013
7.	1st Prize in the NTU's TechFest 30 hours Hackathon 2013 for an e-commerce app that uses computer vision to recommend "matching" fashion accessories.	Feb 2013

Work Experience

DESCRIPTIONS OF RESEARCH PROJECTS AND SELECTED TECHNICAL PROJECTS CAN BE FOUND AT http://prernac.com/

Human-Computer Interaction Institute, Carnegie Mellon University GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT (PHD STUDENT)

Pittsburgh, PA, USA Jul 2017 - PRESENT

- Leveraging passively sensed contextual data from multiple sensors on the user's smartphones and wearables to develop tools that aid in diagnosis, monitoring, and treatment of diseases, and make medicine more precise.
- E.g. Predicting symptoms of depression and loneliness in college students, neurological and mental health symptoms in patients with multiple sclerosis, and understanding the user's context to intervene and reduce problematic smartphone use.

Snap Research (Snapchat)RESEARCH INTERN

New York City, NY May 2020 - Aug 2020

- Supervisors: Brian Smith, Shree Nayar
- Teams: Human-Computer Interaction, Computational Imaging
- Developing a new method of social visual communication. I implemented a novel emoji-first communication app for partners and close friends, that enhanced humor, affection, and creativity by leveraging the shared language formed between partners. I wrote the iOS app in Swift (using CoreML and a Twitter database for NLP) and ran a user study with 22 participants.
- Project not public yet.

Microsoft Research

Cambridge, UK RESEARCH INTERN May 2019 - Sep 2019

- Supervisors: Anja Thieme, Danielle Belgrave
- Teams: Health Intelligence, Human Experience Design and Engineering
- · Worked on analyzing and modeling user interactions with a widely used Digital Mental Health Intervention, in order to recommend changes that would make the intervention more effective.

Human-Computer Interaction Institute, Carnegie Mellon University GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT (MS STUDENT)

Pittsburgh, PA, USA Aug 2015 - Jul 2017

- Studied the physiological and behavioral underpinnings of Team Performance (Collective Intelligence) and Cohesion (Group Satisfaction) using speech, video, and physiological sensor data collected during a video call between 2 people. Our work revealed new relationships between Synchrony in Facial Expressions and Collective Intelligence, and Synchrony in Electrodermal Activity and Group Satisfaction.
- Predicted the outcomes of negotiations between 2 people by applying Multimodal Machine Learning techniques to audio and video recordings of their interaction. Linear Support Vector Machine (LSVM) with Multiple Kernel Learning that learnt different kernels for audio and video features gave a 10% higher accuracy than the LSVM baseline.

Nanyang Technological University PRESIDENT RESEARCH SCHOLAR (SENIOR)

Singapore Sep 2014 - Jun 2015

• Proposed a system to enhance supervised learning for polarity classification by leveraging on linguistic rules based on conjunctions and conditionals. Additionally, built a hybrid classifier by adding an unsupervised classification layer to the supervised classifier. The unsupervised classifier applied rules based on commonsense concepts extracted from text.

Computer Vision Lab, École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne, Switzerland RESEARCH INTERN

Lausanne, Switzerland Aug 2013 - Jan 2014

· Worked on re-identification and tracking of people in sports and pedestrian datasets using appearance cues like color and texture. Implemented and evaluated methods using – (i) dominant colors, (ii) color histograms, and (iii) color invariants.

Computer Graphics Lab, École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne, Switzerland SUMMER RESEARCH INTERN

Lausanne, Switzerland May 2013 - Aug 2013

• Used RGB-D input to track a person's hand in real-time and capture its performance. More specifically – Used RGB-D data to create a 3D mesh of a person's hand in real-time. Multithreading and Optimization was used to improve performance. Hand and fingertips were detected.

Nanyang Technological University

PRESIDENT RESEARCH SCHOLAR (SOPHOMORE)

Singapore Sep 2012 - May 2013

• Conducted a literature review and helped develop an animated "Talking Head" of a living person.

Media Coverage_

- HuffPost. Here's Why Your Next Work Meeting Should Not Be A Zoom Call. June 2021.
- Wall Street Journal. How Videoconferences Make It Harder for Employees to Collaborate. June 2021.
- Forbes. Are Zoom Meetings Reducing Our Collective Intelligence?. April 2021.
- Fast Company. Zoom is actually less effective than a phone call for these types of meetings. March 2021.
- IndiaTV. Disabling video during online meets boosts communication. March 2021.
- The Economic Times (CIO). Disabling video during online meets boosts communication. March 2021.
- Harvard Business Review. Successful Remote Teams Communicate in Bursts. October 2020.

Academic and Professional Service

REVIEWING

- ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI): 2022 (2), 2021 (4), 2020 (2), 2019 (3) **★**Special Recognition for Exceptional Reviewing! 2021 (1), 2019 (1) ★
- ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT): 2021 (1), 2020 (2), 2019 (1) **★**Special Recognition for Exceptional Reviewing! 2020 (1) ★
- Journal of Medical Internet Research (JMIR): 2020 (1)
- ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW): 2018 (2)
- The International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM): 2021 (1), 2020 (1)
- International Conference on Affective Computing & Intelligent Interaction (ACII): 2019 (1)
- International Conference on Multimodal Interaction (ICMI): 2018 (2)

PROGRAM COMMITTEE(S)

1. Workshop on "Machine Learning for the Diagnosis and Treatment of Affective Disorders" at the 8th International Conference on Affective Computing & Intelligent Interaction (ACII)

2019

TEACHING AND COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT

1. **International Student Advocate for CMU's Graduate Student Assembly (GSA)**Led advocacy efforts on the behalf of CMU's International Students. E.g. I advocated for specific changes at the Office of International Education (OIE) to help them better support International Students.

Sep 2020 – May 2021

2. Served on the PhD Admission Committee of Carnegie Mellon University's Human-Computer Interaction Institute

Dec 2020 - Feb 2021

Reviewed applications to the PhD in HCI program and recommended applicants for admission.

3. Facilitator, BiasBusters @ SCS
Facilitated implicit bias training workshops for faculty, students, and staff, under the guidance of Dr. Carol Frieze at CMU.

Spring 2020

4. Graduate Teaching Assistant

Fall 2019

05-430/05-630 Programming Usable Interfaces at Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA, USA

Aug 2012 – May 2014

Vice Chairperson - Internal, IEEE-NTU, Science Symposium Committee
 Organised symposiums in which, high students presented papers on research projects and received feedback from NTU faculty. The goal was to encourage students to pursue STEM careers.

Mar 2013

6. **Instructor, "Web Development" Workshop, Computer Engineering Club, NTU**Created the curriculum and taught 40 school students the basics of HTML and helped them create their first website which was hosted online, during a Community Involvement Program.

Mar 2013

7. **Instructor, "Google Search Techniques", Computer Engineering Club, NTU**Created the curriculum and taught 40 school students how to perform web searches and filter the results.

Dec 2012

Skills

LANGUAGES AND TOOLS

Programming Python, R, Matlab, Android, Swift (iOS), C/C++, Qt (with C++), Java, OpenCV, OpenGL, OCaml

Data Science Scikit-learn, Pandas, MySql, R, NLTK, SPSS, Tableau

Hardware Arduino, Particle's Photon, Verilog (Hardware Description Language)

Web Dev PHP, JSP, HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, jQuery **Human** English (native), Hindi (native), French (beginner)

References

PHD Advisors

- Anind Dey: Dean, Information School, University of Washington, Seattle, WA.
- Mayank Goel: Assistant Professor, School of Computer Science, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA.

RESEARCH INTERNSHIP ADVISORS IN THE INDUSTRY

At Microsoft Research:

- Anja Thieme: Senior Researcher, Microsoft Research, Cambridge, UK.
- Danielle Belgrave: Principal Researcher, Microsoft Research, Cambridge, UK.

At Snap Research (Snapchat):

- Brian Smith: Research Scientist at Snap Inc. and Assistant Professor of Computer Science at Columbia University.
- Shree Nayar: Director of NYC Research at Snap Inc. and Professor of Computer Science at Columbia University.

MASTERS ADVISOR AND COLLABORATOR

- · Laura Dabbish: Associate Professor, School of Computer Science, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA.
- Anita Woolley: Assistant Professor, Tepper School of Business, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA.